ZHUTIAN CHEN · CURRICULUM VITAE

☑ zhutian.chen@connect.ust.hk • ② chenzhutian.org • Last Updated Feb. 05th, 2020

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Data Visualization, Human-Computer Interaction, Machine Learning, Augmented Reality.

My research seeks to enable futuristic data analysis and communication – powered by Artificial Intelligence and presented by Augmented Reality (AR). To this end, I study the ways to leverage machine learning to assist humain in creating and interacting with data visualizations in AR, as well as leveraging visualizations to assist human in understanding and diagnosing machine learning models.

EDUCATION

EDUCATION		
09/2015 - Present	Hong Kong University of Science & Technology, Kowloon, Hong Kong Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science & Engineering Advisor: Huamin Qu Awarded Hong Kong Ph.D. Fellowship	
09/2011 - 07/2015	South China University of Technology, Guangzhou, China B.S. in Software Engineering Advisor: Yi Cai Awarded Pacemaker to Merit Student, the Highest Honor (top 0.01%)	
POSITIONS		
09/2015 - Present	Hong Kong University of Science & Technology, Kowloon, Hong Kong Graduate Researcher - VISLab	

POSITIONS	
09/2015 - Present	Hong Kong University of Science & Technology, Kowloon, Hong Kong Graduate Researcher - VISLab Advisor: Huamin Qu
09/2019 - 12/2019	The University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK Research Visiting Student - Design Informatics Advisor: Benjamin Bach
08/2017 - 11/2017	ByteDance , Beijing, China Software Engineering Intern - Big Data Platform Group Advisor: Liang Tang
06/2017 - 08/2017	FIT Future Information Technology, Beijing, China Research Intern - SLAM Group Advisor: Kaidi Zhou
Spring/2015, 2017	State Key Lab of CAD&CG, Hangzhou, China Research Assistant - ZJU VIS Advisor: Yingcai Wu
06/2014 - 01/2015	Microsoft Research Asia, Beijing, China Research Intern - Internet Graphics Group Advisor: Yingcai Wu

PEER REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

- 2019 C7 **Zhutian Chen**, Wai Tong, Qianwen Wang, Benjamin Bach, and Huamin Qu. "Augmenting Static Visualizations with PapARVis Designer." *ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems* (*CHI*'20). 24% acceptance rate, 10 pages
 - C5, J5 **Zhutian Chen**, Yun Wang, Qianwen Wang, Yong Wang, and Huamin Qu. "Towards Automated Infographic Design: Deep Learning-based Auto-Extraction of Extensible Timeline." *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics* (*Info-Vis'19*). 24% acceptance rate, 10 pages
 - C4, J4 **Zhutian Chen**, Wei Zeng, Zhiguang Yang, Lingyun Yu, Chi-Wing Fu, and Huamin Qu. "LassoNet: Deep Lasso-Selection of 3D Point Clouds." *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics* (SciVis'19). 25% acceptance rate, 10 pages
- 2018 J3 **Zhutian Chen**, Yijia Su, Yifang Wang, Qianwen Wang, Huamin Qu, Yingcai Wu. "MARVisT: Authoring Glyph-based Visualization in Mobile Augmented Reality." *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (TVCG)*.
- Zhutian Chen, Yifang Wang, Tianchen Sun, Xiang Gao, Wei Chen, Zhigeng Pan, Huamin Qu, Yingcai Wu. "Exploring the Design Space of Immersive Urban Analytics." *Journal of Visual Informatics (JVI)*.
 - Yingcai Wu, Zhutian Chen, Guodao Sun, Xiao Xie, Nan Cao, Shixia Liu, Weiwei Cui. "StreamExplorer: A Multi-Stage System for Visually Exploring Events in Social Streams." IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (TVCG).
 - W1 **Zhutian Chen**, Huamin Qu, Yingcai Wu. "Immersive Urban Analytics through Exploded Views." *IEEE VIS 2017 Workshop on Immersive Analytics*.
- 2016 C3 Yun Wang, **Zhutian Chen**, Quan Li, Xiaojuan Ma, Qiong Luo, Huamin Qu. "Animated Narrative Visualization for Video Clickstream Data." *ACM SIGGRAPH ASIA Visualization Symposium (SIGGRAPH ASIA)*.
 - C2 Mingqian Zhao, **Zhutian Chen**, Ke Lu, Chaoran Li, Huamin Qu, Xiaojuan Ma. "Blossom: Design of a Tangible Interface for Improving Intergenerational Communication for the Elderly." *ACM Interactive Technology and Ageing Populations (ITAP)*.
 - Yun Wang, Tongshuang Wu, **Zhutian Chen**, Qiong Luo, Huamin Qu. "STAC: Enhancing Stacked Graphs for Time Series Analysis." *IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium (PacificVis)*.

AWARDS AND HONORS

- 2019 2020 **Overseas Research Award** Hong Kong University of Science & Technology
- 2019 2020 **Research Travel Grant**Hong Kong University of Science & Technology

2018 - 2019	Research Travel Grant Hong Kong University of Science & Technology	
08/2016	First Prize of the Design Thinking China Academy of Art, Hong Kong University of Science & Technology	
2015 - 2019	Hong Kong Ph.D. Fellowship (HKPFS) Research Grants Council of Hong Kong	
01/2015	Award of Excellence Microsoft Research Asia	
2013 - 2014	Pacemaker to Merit Student South China University of Technology, the highest honor (top 0.1%)	
2013 - 2014	National Scholarship Ministry of Education of the People's Republic of China	
04/2014	Meritorious Winner of Interdisciplinary Contest in Modeling Consortium for Mathematics and Its Applications, USA	
2013 - 2014	Tencent Technology Excellence Scholarship Tencent Holdings Limited	
2012 - 2013	National Scholarship Ministry of Education of the People's Republic of China	
2011 - 2012	National Scholarship for Encouragement Ministry of Education of the People's Republic of China	
INVITED TALKS		
01/2020 12/2019 11/2019 07/2019	Towards Futuristic Visual StoryTelling: Authoring Data-Driven Infographics in Augmented Reality Shandong University, Qingdao, China Ant Financial, Hangzhou, China The University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK Zhejiang Lab, Hangzhou, China	
10/2019	Towards Automated Infographic Design: Deep Learning-based Auto-Extraction of Extensible Timeline IEEE VIS'19, Vancouver, Canada	
10/2019	MARVisT: Authoring Glyph-based Visualization in Mobile Augmented Reality IEEE VIS'19, Vancouver, Canada	
10/2019	LassoNet: Deep Lasso-Selection of 3D Point Clouds IEEE VIS'19, Vancouver, Canada	
10/2019	InfoVis in Augmented Reality ARVis Meet-up@Microsoft, Vancouver, Canada	
	StreamExplorer: A Multi-Stage System for Visually Exploring Events in Social Streams	

10/2018	IEEE VIS'18, Berlin, Germany		
12/2016	Animated Narrative Visualization for Video Clickstream Data Visualization Symposium at ACM SIGGRAPH ASIA'16, Macao, China		
TEACHING			
TEACHING			
Fall/2018	Teaching Assistant , COMP2711: Discrete Mathematical Tools for Computer Science, HKUST.		
Spring/2018	Teaching Assistant, COMP4901f: Data Visualization, HKUST.		
MENTORING			
Summer/2019	Wai Tong (M.Phil. at HKUST): [C7].		
Spring/2019	Zhiguang Yang (M.S. at SIAT, Chinese Academy of Sciences): [C4, J4].		
2017 - 2018	Yifang Wang (Ph.D. at HKUST): [J3, J2].		
Spring/2017	Tianchen Sun (B.S. at ZJU, now Ph.D. at UC Davis with Kwan-Liu Ma): [J2].		
Spring/2017	Xiang Gao (M.S. at ZJU): [J2].		
2016 - 2017	Zhen Li (M.Phil at HKUST): E-l	earning Project.	
2016 - 2017	Shaozu Cao (Ph.D. at HKUST): E-learning Project.		
SERVICE			
2020	Paper Reviewer, CG&A (IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications)		
2020	Paper Reviewer, CHI (ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems)		
2019	Paper Reviewer, PacificVis		
2019	Paper Reviewer, TOG (ACM Transactions on Graphics)		
2019	Paper Reviewer, VRST (ACM Virtual Reality Software and Technology)		
2019	Paper Reviewer, ChinaVis		
2019	Paper Reviewer, VIS (IEEE Visualization Conference)		
2018	Paper Reviewer, VIS (IEEE Vis	sualization Conference)	
REFERENCE			
Huamin Qu		Yingcai Wu	
Professor of Computer Science		ZJU100 Young Professor of Computer Science	
Hong Kong University of Science & Technology		Zhejiang University	
huamin@cse.ust.h	ık	ycwu@zju.edu.cn	

Benjamin Bach

Lecturer of Design Informatics and Visualization the University of Edinburgh bbach@inf.ed.ac.uk